Finding Aid for Philomena Falls Papers, 1927-1986
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Philomena Falls papers 1927-1986
Falls, Philomena.
1.3 linear ft. and 6 oversize volumes
86425 Aa 2
Teacher, member of Women's Army Auxiliary Corps during World War II, later teacher in school for children of military personnel in Germany, 1946-1949, and Japan, 1954-1955. Letters describing her life and activities in Germany and Japan; letters from friend Fred Reynolds; and scrapbooks-photograph albums from stays in Europe and Japan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Philomena Falls (donor no. 5931 ) and came to the library in several accessions.
The collection is open to research.
Philomena Falls served with the Women's Army Auxiliary Corps during World War II. After the war, she returned to Germany where she was a teacher in the Army of Occupation school system. She also taught in Japan in 1954-1955, then returned to Michigan to teach in public schools, later becoming a principal.
The collection consists of correspondence, scrapbooks, and photograph albums. The collection is of primary value for its documentation, both printed and visual, of Philomena Falls service with the Women's Army Auxiliary Corps and for her extended stays in Germany and Japan as a teacher.
Subjects:
Germany.; Japan.; Teachers--Japan.; Teachers--Germany.; United States. Army. Women's Army Auxiliary Corps.; Women teachers--Japan.; Women teachers--Germany.; World War, 1939-1945--Participation, Female.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Falls, Philomena.; Travel--Europe.; Travel--Germany.; Travel--Japan.; United States. Army. Women's Army Auxiliary Corps.; Women--War.
Contributors:
Reynolds, Fred.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  - Biographical information / miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Letters to friend Faye while in the WACs, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
  - Travel letters written from Germany, 1946-1949 (Box 1)
  - Travel letters written from Japan, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - Letters from friend, Fred Reynolds, 1927-1986, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Postcards and greeting cards from friend (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks
  (include some photographs; these volumes were probably created close to the dates of the materials)
  - Germany, Book 1, 1946-1949 (Box 2)
    (include clippings, travel brochures, postcards, and memorabilia)
  - Germany, Book 2, 1948-1949 (Box 2)
    (include clippings, travel brochures, and memorabilia)
  - Japan, Book 1, 1954-1955 (Box 2)
  - Japan, Book 1, 1954-1955 (Box 2)
    (include clippings, photographs, travel brochures, postcards, and memorabilia)
- Photograph albums / Scrapbooks
  (these volumes, although they have dates similar to the scrapbook series, were probably put into albums at a later date)
  - Women's Army Auxiliary Corps, Book 1, 1943 (Volume 1)
    (include clippings, photographs, military memoranda, travel brochures, postcards, and memorabilia)
    (oversize vol. 1)
  - Women's Army Auxiliary Corps, Book 2, 1944-1945 (Volume 2)
    (oversize vol. 2)
  - Germany, Book 1, 1946-1949 (Volume 3)
    (mainly photographs of places and sites throughout West Germany)
    (oversize vol. 3)
  - Germany, Book 2, 1948-1949 (Volume 4)
    (oversize vol. 4)
  - European travels: Austria, Belgium, Czechoslovakia, Denmark, France, Great Britain, 1947-1949 (Volume 5)
    (primarily brochures, receipts, clippings)
    (oversize vol. 5)
  - European travels: Italy, Luxembourg, North Africa, Netherlands, Norway, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland, 1947-1949 (Volume 6)
    (oversize vol. 6)